hello there and welcome the first full
videos have been about outlining the
problems and the destructive dynamics
that have always persisted in game a and
quite frankly I coulda made a hundred
videos about problems with game a but
the point is that all of those hundred
videos you'd also might be able to trace
the source of the problem back to some
combination of those three dynamics that
I've laid out so future videos are going
to be about how to tackle those dynamics
and before I go any further I need to
introduce the notion of the generator
function and this is incredibly powerful
idea the Mandelbrot set that I showed
you in the last video it's a shape it's
an infinitely complex shape and what is
zoomed in on is the boundary of that
shape now that shape is created by the
running of one very simple function here
it is said goes to Z squared plus C and
so this idea of a simple thing iterated
lots of times being able to create
something as magnificent and as complex
as the Mandelbrot set is but for me at
least a really key idea I mean this is
my personal perspective on game B other
people involved in the game B project
have very different perspectives and
that's not only okay it's actually great
it's a strength and that's one of the
things that this video is about so bear
in mind that this is my personal
perspective on it but if you accept the
notion that human society is a complex
system and that each of us as
individuals are nodes in that system
then the culture the society as a whole
is the sum of all the generator
functions run by those nodes in the
network right and so if we are all
running rival richness and
responsiveness to broadcast modality and
an insistence on using complicatedness
then that is the society that is the
culture that we that we were building
that we will manifest and if there is
some way to change the generator
functions and push those to the side or
at least strongly de-emphasize them and
replace them then game becomes about as
a consequence of that so that's the
that's the context that I would like to
put the rest of this video into
and now I'm going to talk about ruler
maker itself and in order to do that I'm
going to use an extremely simple example
to make the point that I want to make
and so if you can envisage a cylinder
the shape of cylinder and then you've
got two people looking at that cylinder
one from the side on and one from above
the one looking from the side sees a
rectangle right the one looking from
above sees a circle and they were both
swear to a court in law to either swear
in a court of law that I'm seeing
rectangle I'm seeing a circle and you
know one of two there's one of two ways
that this can play out they can either
spend you know however long arguing with
each other you're an idiot you're an
idiot don't you know a circle and you
see one or they can accept the
possibility that maybe there's a deeper
truth here that neither of them are
grasping right and that if they can find
a way of effectively combining their
perspectives perhaps they can achieve
that deeper understanding right so
that's that's the that's the heart of
rule Omega and everybody has valid
perspective I it goes both ways
I have valid perspective to bring to
this situation but I also understand
that my perspective is incomplete
equally you have a valid point of view
to bring to this problem or situation
but yours is also incomplete right and
so if we can find a way to enter into a
dialogue such that we can understand and
enter into the other's perspective while
at the same time hanging on to our own
not abandoning our own then there is an
opportunity for deeper truths to be
grasped that neither of us could grasp
on our own
another important aspect of rule Omega
is the idea of humility so you're not
turning up in you're not turning up in
the conversation to say what you've
already got in your head right it's not
like a normal conversation where
oftentimes you're sitting waiting for
Paul so that you can say what you've
already got any wine to say right no
it's it's it's more about you offer
yourself up as a humble vessel through
which that which wishes to be expressed
can be expressed and so this can be
extremely difficult
I mean rule Omega on the one hand is
very simple I'm going to explain it in
five minutes on the other hand though
it's extremely difficult it requires a
good degree of honest self-examination
and humility and dealing with your
basically and before you can be an
effective engage in this kind of in this
kind of interaction rule Omega is
something that you do it's not something
you talk about I know how many I know
I'm sitting here talking about it now
but I would say one of the key key
skills that is required for rule Omega
is discernment and I mean this in two
ways firstly where I've already alluded
to you know that you're speaking from a
place not of ego not I wish to be seen
not I want to look clever not I haven't
spoken for a few minutes it feels like
it's my turn you know not not that kind
of stuff but when when something that
feels like it's right in the moment that
it's going to help and that it's going
to expand the the expand the
conversation then then that is when you
speak and and this is extremely
difficult right I mean I again it's it's
easy to say it's much more difficult to
do the second part of discernment is the
understanding that what the other person
is expressing they may not be expressing
it very well right I mean you're talking
about difficult things very possibly
you're in territory that you've never
been in before and so try as you might
it's very possible you not going to
explain yourself as well as you might be
given a little bit of time to process it
and so my job as the listener is to even
though you will not say it very well to
separate out the signal from the noise
and homing this homed in on the signal
and then okay I think what you are
trying to say is something like this and
I and I then say it back in such a way
that maybe enables you to say us a
little bit more clearly and by this
iterative process we get to something
right now this is you know I put this in
the situation of two people just make it
simple but obviously the more
perspectives that can be brought to
these kinds of conversations the more
possibility there is for exploration
effort and for deep uncovering of
something new I really like the analogy
of the jazz band that I've heard Jamie
in Jordan news past and so in a jazz
band he got four or five people whatever
sitting around riffing jamming and one
of them sort of it catches their if
something catches their ear that oh oh
oh I like that I can do something with
that what do you think this and oh yeah
yeah that gives me an idea this would go
really well with this how do you think
these two things with gel together and
so on and so on and so on and and by
this iterative process that I've just
talked about something amazing can
emerge I'd like to come back to kind of
what
at the beginning that rule Omega is
potentially an incredibly powerful
generator function because it cuts off
all three the rival rusts the
complicated and the broad cuts them all
off at the knees right it is
fundamentally anti rivals in the same
way that jazz band is you can't turn up
with your own agenda right I've got this
thing that I want to do it creation
doesn't work like that right it doesn't
hit nothing is going to emerge at that
kind of mindset so it's fundamentally
anti rivals and and not just non ante
because you're creating things with none
of you could have possibly created on
your own you arrived basis none of you
could have got to on your own and
because you've created something new
it's soil on which more new things can
be built afterwards so it's absolutely
anti rivalry it's interfaces with the
complex because you know a session of a
dozen people whatever having a
conversation these are complex beings
interacting in complex ways right and so
complexity is is stamped right into
anything that emerges from that and it
is as I said in an earlier video the
absolute antithesis of the broadcast
modality because there is no person in
charge there's no one setting agenda
there's no top-down kind of structure
whatsoever here the other thing that's
very cool about blue lawmaker is that
it's it's an actual thing that you can
do yeah that any individual can start
doing right now get a few people
together you know understand what Lula
mega-bear and start practicing you know
it'll feel weird and clumsy would have
to start with but if nothing else it
will improve your own personal
relationships that is also an
opportunity for at an individual level
people start feeling that they have a
meaningful and important and immediate
role to play in the transmutation of
game a into game B it can be a real
source of frustration not to feel like
you as an individual matter but this is
absolutely not the case you know and and
the groups that you form will be
potentially seeds for decentralized
intelligence networks which can grow
from them so you know it's a real thing
it's not pie in the sky I would
particularly like to point you at the
three-way conversation between Janie
Weil Jordan
smacking burger that was on rebel wisdom
and again link below in which they talk
about among other things rule Omega but
what's cool about it is that they sort
of embody it's used during the
conversation as well as it's a really
excellent place to start to explore
these ideas a little bit further so yeah
thank you very much addy for watching
all of these this kind of concludes game
b101
foundation cause the future videos that
I'm going to make are going to be about
the protocols the generative functions
and most importantly the skills that we
as individuals can begin to cultivate in
order to make us better runners of those
generator functions and in doing so game
B will come about on its own I mean it's
another feature of complex systems as if
you alter the generator functions that
the modes of running the system will
reorganize a whole new system will
emerge from that right and so if if
enough of us can change our generator
functions then the gain changes as a
consequence of that right without having
to actually change the game from the top
down